Intel(R) DIAGS Release Notes
============================
June 18, 2019

Contents
========
- OVERVIEW
- COMMAND LINE PARAMETERS
- NOTES
- INSTALLATION
- CUSTOMER SUPPORT
- LEGAL


OVERVIEW
========
Intel's diagnostic software lets you test the adapter to see if there are any
problems with the adapter hardware, the cabling, or the network connection. You
can also use diagnostics to isolate problems during troubleshooting. DIAGS is a
single program that operates identically
under multiple operating systems.

These utilities are designed to test hardware operation and confirm the
adapter's ability to communicate with another adapter in the same network,
primarily confirming cabling. They should not be used to judge performance.

They can test the adapter whether or not there is a responder on the network.
In order to do a thorough test, however, you should set-up a second system on
the network as a responder prior to starting a test.

Notes:
- On the Intel(R) Ethernet Switch FM10000 Host Interface, loopback diagnostic
tests, and other tests that rely on the loopback test, will fail if the Switch
Manager is not running.
- These tools no longer support Linux on Itanium(R)-based systems.


COMMAND LINE PARAMETERS
=======================
- VERSION Print Diags version information.
- ? Print command line usage instructions.


NOTES
=====
- In general for any OS this utility may unload (or set to idle) the drivers
  for the adapters selected through this utility, if they were loaded.


Installation
=============


INSTALLING THE TOOL ON MICROSOFT* WINDOWS*
===========================================

To install the tools' drivers on Windows, run install.bat from the appropriate
directory of the install package.

Although the tool are not installed with install.bat, the driver that the tool
requires is copied into the local machine Windows driver directory. To run the
tool, launch a Command Prompt window from the Windows Start Menu. Go to the
media and directory where the tool is located and run the utility. The readme
files for each tool are found in the same directory as the tool. These tools
can be manually installed on the local hard drive in any directory.

The tool uses its own driver file (not the same as the system network driver).
If the driver sys file already exists in the drivers directory, install.bat may
fail to copy. Using the /y switch with install.bat will override and copy the
driver file regardless. However, this can be dangerous if an older version of
the driver is being used by another application such as Intel(R) PROSet for
Windows Device Manager. If a driver is already present in the drivers
directory, try running the tool from the command prompt. If it runs, then the
driver is fine. The tool will not run if the driver version present does not
match the driver version expected.

Note that you must have access to the %systemroot%\system32\drivers directory.
Only the administrator account has these privileges. You must be logged in as
administrator or the tools must be run as administrator.

Note that on Windows, any device that is disabled in device manager will not be
accessible by tools due to no memory resources. You would get an error code
0xC86A800E. To solve this problem, you can do one of the following:
1) Re-enable the device in device manager. Never disable this device when
   using tools.
2) Install an NDIS device driver for the device and make sure that it does
   not have a yellow or red bang by it in device manager.
3) Delete the device from device manager and restart the system. The install
   new hardware wizard should appear on next reboot. Do not cancel this. Just
   move the window aside and run the tool(s). Generally, you can click "cancel"
   on the wizard but there are some cases where Windows will disable the memory
   resources causing you to get back into the same state.


INSTALLING THE TOOLS ON EFI
===========================

The EFI 1.x tools are not supported in this release.
These tools no longer support EFI on Itanium(R)-based systems.

There is no installation required for EFI tools. The tools can simply be copied
from the appropriate directory to the drive that they will run from. The EFI2
binaries are for use with the UEFI Shell 2.X with the UEFI 2.3 HII protocol.
EFI2 tools will not run on the EFI Shell 1.X or if the UEFI 2.3 HII protocol is
not present.

Note that while EFI supports USB drives, there may be issues running tools from
the USB drive. Whether or not there are issues are BIOS specific. If you
experience issues, run the tool from hard disk instead.


INSTALLING THE TOOLS ON DOS
===========================

The tools support various DOS versions. There is no installation required for
DOS tools. The tools can simply be copied from the DOS directory on the CD to
the drive that they will run from. It is expected that the tools have a clean
boot environment. The tools will not run with memory managers and/or DOS
networking drivers loaded. The tools expect that they have full, unlimited
control of the hardware. The tools *WILL NOT* run properly if EMM386 is
present. The tools run in protected mode, 32-bit DOS. Therefore, they will not
be compatible with any TSR programs.


INSTALLING THE TOOLS ON LINUX*
==============================

These tools no longer support Linux on Itanium(R)-based systems.
In order to run tools on Linux*, a driver stub must be built and installed on
the system. This driver is not related to the network device driver that is
used to run the network during live traffic. It is a separate driver used
explicitly for tools. Due to the nature of Linux with the number of kernels
that can exist, we provide source for the driver module and an install script
to build/install it.

The tools support Linux distributions based on kernels 2.6.x. Validation is
done randomly on popular distributions such as Red Hat* or Suse*. Configured
kernel source that matches the currently installed kernel is required. A
working GCC is also required. There are some versions of GCC that had a bug
which did not support unnamed structures. These versions of GCC are not
supported. If you have compilation errors, try updating your version of GCC. If
you have linker errors when installing the driver, you should update your
kernel - download the latest stable off www.kernel.org and build/install it.

Note that some distributions such as recent Fedora core versions do not ship
with Kernel source. You must download, install, and configure the source in
order to get the tools' driver built on this OS. Installing the kernel source
RPM does not solve the problem.

On kernel 4.16 or higher, ensure iomem parameter set to relaxed
---------------------------------------------------------------
On Linux* kernel 4.16 and higher, the iomem parameter is set to "strict" by
default, which prevents the NVM update utilities from accessing the MMIO on
1GbE and 10GbE devices. Trying to update a device when "strict" is set causes
the device to lose link during the update process. Also, if you run any of the
NVM update utilities (NVMUpdate, NVMCheck, QCU, or Bootutil), the utility may
exit with the error "The selected adapter (location:[Bus:Device:Function])
cannot be initialized due to inaccessible device memory. Update the device
driver and reboot the system before running this utility again. Consult the
utility documentation for more information."

If you wish to update a device without losing link, you can either:
1. Install Linux base drivers (igb or ixgbe) from Release 24.1, or newer
2. Set the iomem kernel parameter to "relaxed" (i.e., iomem=relaxed) and reboot
the system before running the update utility.

This is the installation procedure:
  1. Log in as root and create a temporary directory to build the Intel(R)
     Network Connection Tools driver.
  2. Copy 'install' and 'iqvlinux.tar.gz' to the temporary directory.
     There are 2 versions of Linux supported: Linux32 (x86)and Linux_x64 (x64).
     Copies of the above files exist in the appropriate directory for your
platform.
  3. CD to the temporary directory and run './install.' The driver has been
     installed now, so the files in the temporary directory can be removed.
  4. Copy the tools that you want to use from the appropriate directory of
     the CD.


INSTALLING THE TOOLS ON FreeBSD*
================================

In order to run tools on FreeBSD*, a driver stub must be built and installed on
the system. This driver is not related to the network device driver that is
used to run the network during live traffic. It is a separate driver used
explicitly for tools. Due to the nature of FreeBSD with the number of kernels
that can exist, we provide source for the driver module and an install script
to build/install it.

The tools support FreeBSD distributions version 10.1 and later.

This is the installation procedure:
  1. Log in as root and create a temporary directory to build the Intel(R)
     Network Connection Tools driver.
  2. Copy 'install' and 'iqvfreebsd.tar' to the temporary directory.
     There are 2 versions of FreeBSD supported: FreeBSD32 (x86) and
     FreeBSD64e (x64). Copies of the above files exist in the appropriate
     directory for your platform.
  3. CD to the temporary directory and run './install' The driver has
     been installed now, so the files in the temporary directory can be
     removed.
  4. Copy the tools that you want to use from the appropriate directory of
     the CD.


CUSTOMER SUPPORT
================
- Main Intel web support site: http://support.intel.com

- Network products information: http://www.intel.com/network


Legal / Disclaimers
===================
Copyright (C) 2002 - 2019, Intel Corporation. All rights reserved.

Intel Corporation assumes no responsibility for errors or omissions in this
document. Nor does Intel make any commitment to update the information
contained herein.

Intel and the Intel logo are trademarks of Intel Corporation or its
subsidiaries in the U.S. and/or other countries.
Itanium is a trademark or registered trademark of Intel Corporation or its
subsidiaries in the U.S. and/or other countries.

*Other names and brands may be claimed as the property of others.

This software is furnished under license and may only be used or copied in
accordance with the terms of the license. The information in this manual is
furnished for informational use only, is subject to change without notice, and
should not be construed as a commitment by Intel Corporation. Intel Corporation
assumes no responsibility or liability for any errors or inaccuracies that may
appear in this document or any software that may be provided in association
with this document. Except as permitted by such license, no part of this
document may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any
form or by any means without the express written consent of Intel Corporation.
