IDADAPT - Intel PCI NIC Identification Utility
==============================================
November 2, 2015

CONTENTS
========
- OVERVIEW
- RUNNING THE UTILITY
- USAGE NOTES
- EXAMPLES
- LIMITATIONS
- DRIVER TO PCI ID CROSS REFERENCE


OVERVIEW
========

The Intel PCI NIC Identification Utility identifies Intel PCI adapters and
provides adapter properties and assigned resources. You can readily use this
information in batch, script and configuration files for automation purposes.

The utility returns the following values:

- Slot number. PCI slot number reported by the adapter; returned in decimal
format.

- SLOTX. PCI slot number reported by the adapter; For Gigabit solutions it is
returned in hexidecimal format.

- PCI device ID. Adapters sharing the same PCI device ID can use the same
driver. See the table at the end of this document showing the relationship
between drivers and PCI device IDs.

- SSID - PCI Subsystem ID and the Subvendor ID displayed in hexidecimal.

- MAC address. 12-digit Ethernet ID assigned to the adapter. This number is
also printed on the adapter label.

- Revision ID. Adapters with the same device ID may be distinguished with the
revision ID.


RUNNING THE UTILITY
===================
Using the "/?" option will display a list of supported command line options.
To run IDADAPT.EXE, you must start the computer in DOS. This utility should not
be run from a command prompt within any version of Microsoft Windows*, or in
any other non-DOS operating system. This utility should not be run with any
memory managers (such as EMM386) loaded.

IDADAPT.EXE can be run with no command line options, or with either of the
following command line options:

/B:<filename>
  Creates a file containing the adapter properties with the name specified. This
  file is in the format of a DOS batch file. If this file is named with the
  extension of .BAT, it can be executed as a batch file. Executing this batch
  file will create environment variables from the adapter properties.

/VERSION
  Displays IDADAPT version information and the diagnostic library version
  information.


NOTES
=====
IDADAPT.EXE will detect and return information on a maximum of sixteen adapters
in a computer.

Running the utility with no command line parameters displays the adapter
properties on the screen. For example, if you enter IDADAPT in a computer with
2 Intel PCI adapters installed, the display would resemble the following:

NIC1 SLOT=43 SLOTX=0068 PCI ID=1229 SSID=10118086 MAC=0002B31FE072 RevID=65
NIC2 SLOT=47 SLOTX=0069 PCI ID=1031 SSID=10118086 MAC=0090270AAF73 RevID=32

In the above example, the first adapter has the following properties:
- Logical slot is 43
- SLOTX is 0068
- PCI device ID is 1229
- SSID is 10118086
- MAC address is 0002B31FE072
- The revision ID is 65

If the utility does not find any adapters, it reports "No supported adapters
were found" and returns an error level of 1. You can use the error level for
conditional branching in batch files.

If you run the utility using /B:<filename>, it creates a file with the name you
specified. This file contains adapter properties in a batch file format. This
is an example batch file:

SET NIC1_SLOT=43
SET NIC1_SLOTX=0068
SET NIC1_PCIID=1229
SET NIC1_SSID=10118086
SET NIC1_MAC=0002B31FE072
SET NIC1_REVID=65
SET NIC2_SLOT=47
SET NIC2_SLOTX=0069
SET NIC2_PCIID=1031
SET NIC2_SSID=10118086
SET NIC2_MAC=0090270AAF73
SET NIC2_REVID=32

If the name you assign to the file ends in .BAT, it can be executed in DOS.
Executing the file sets environment variables for each property of each adapter.

Once the environment variables are created by the batch file, you can insert
the values into configuration files as needed. See examples below. When using
this batch file, remember that about 64 bytes of environment space will be
needed for each adapter found. Ensure that you make sufficient environment
space available in your configuration.


EXAMPLES
========

Example 1:
To create a startup disk that loads a Packet Driver named PCKTDRVR.COM on the
second found NIC, the AUTOEXEC.BAT file might contain the following:
IDADAPT /B:INTELSET.BAT
IF ERRORLEVEL 1 GOTO NO_NIC
CALL INTELSET.BAT
PCKTDRVR 0x60 %NIC2_SLOT%
GOTO END
:NO_NIC
ECHO NO ADAPTER FOUND!!
PAUSE
:END

Example 2:
To create a startup disk that automatically detects the adapter model and loads
the proper DOS ODI driver, the AUTOEXEC.BAT file might contain the following:
IDADAPT /B:INTELSET.BAT
IF ERRORLEVEL 1 GOTO NO_NIC
CALL INTELSET.BAT
LSL
IF "%NIC1_PCIID%" == "1229" GOTO PRO100
IF "%NIC1_PCIID%" == "2449" GOTO PRO100
IF "%NIC1_PCIID%" == "1000" GOTO PRO1000
IF "%NIC1_PCIID%" == "1001" GOTO PRO1000
IF "%NIC1_PCIID%" == "1002" GOTO PRO1000
IF "%NIC1_PCIID%" == "1003" GOTO PRO1000
IF "%NIC1_PCIID%" == "1004" GOTO PRO1000
GOT0 NO_NIC
:PRO100
E100BODI
GOTO CONTINUE
:PRO1000
E1000ODI
GOTO CONTINUE
:CONTINUE
IPXODI
VLM /V4
GOTO END
:NO_NIC
ECHO !! NO SUITABLE ADAPTER FOUND !!
PAUSE
:END


CUSTOMER SUPPORT
================
- Main Intel web support site: http://support.intel.com

- Network products information: http://www.intel.com/network


Legal / Disclaimers
===================
Copyright (C) 2003 - 2015, Intel Corporation. All rights reserved.

Intel Corporation assumes no responsibility for errors or omissions in this
document. Nor does Intel make any commitment to update the information
contained herein.

Intel and the Intel logo are trademarks of Intel Corporation or its
subsidiaries in the U.S. and/or other countries.

*Other names and brands may be claimed as the property of others.

This software is furnished under license and may only be used or copied in
accordance with the terms of the license. The information in this manual is
furnished for informational use only, is subject to change without notice, and
should not be construed as a commitment by Intel Corporation. Intel Corporation
assumes no responsibility or liability for any errors or inaccuracies that may
appear in this document or any software that may be provided in association
with this document. Except as permitted by such license, no part of this
document may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system, or transmitted in any
form or by any means without the express written consent of Intel Corporation.
